Stamatina (Matina) Thomaidou, Ph.D.

Contact Information $\hbox{\it E-mail:} thomaidou.matina@gmail.com$

matinathomaidou.github.io Location: Dublin, Ireland

Summary

Marketing Science Auction Expert at Facebook, helping clients to strategically optimize their performance in the Ad Auction. Prior to Facebook, worked at IBM Ireland as Data Science Leader for Europe, Accenture Greece, Microsoft Norway, and Ecole Polytechnique in France, leading data science and business insights projects.

Professional Experience

Facebook, Marketing Science Auction Expert (June 2018 - Present)

• Helping clients to strategically optimize their performance in the Ad Auction.

IBM Digital Sales, Data Science Leader for Europe, Data Science and Optimization Global Team - Innovation Lab (June 2017 - May 2018)

- Led project to build and deploy globally a recommendation engine for sales plays, products, and whitespace prospects. Collaborated with cross-functional teams to ensure its successful scaling and deployment for our 5000+ digital sellers worldwide. Our work has been referenced by Harvard Business Review.
- Empowered global sales acceleration team efforts to drive business results for the commercial segment by producing recommendations for new product campaigns resulting to \$17M 3Q pipeline and \$1M revenue.

IBM Digital Sales, Senior Data Scientist, Data Science and Optimization Global Team - Innovation Lab (June 2015 - May 2017)

- Developed and deployed an evidence-based capability for assessing seller skills.
- Accelerated revenue growth and improved seller productivity with data-driven territory management. Power and Storage missions reversed the declines of 2014 and achieved double-digit YTY growth.
- Recruited and advised mentees. Technical Supervisor and Mentor for IBM Ireland UCD Smurfit School MSc Business Analytics Project for 2016 & 2017.

Accenture Digital, Analytics & Data Management Senior Analyst (October 2014 - May 2015)

Global Telecommunications Company Client, Digital Marketing & Web Analytics

• Deployed solutions that helped clients across 16 countries to optimize the value they derive from their digital strategies.

Global Retail Company Client, Marketing Analytics

• Assessed the effectiveness of key marketing and trade activities and provided the client with an optimized promotional strategy.

Microsoft Development Center Norway, Program Manager Intern (June 2014 - August 2014)

Office Graph and Delve

- Won the Ship it! Award (Microsoft Internal Hackathon at Oslo).
- Identified patterns among query failures in the Graph Index Test Environment to enable developers automate their tests.

Laboratoire d'Informatique de l'École Polytechnique (LIX), Researcher & Software Engineer (November 2012 - January 2013)

Extended the capabilities of a prototype Real Time Bidder into a scalable architecture.

Data & Web Mining Group of Athens University of Economics and Business, Ph.D. Researcher (March 2011 - October 2014)

- PhD in "Machine Learning Methods for Online Advertising Campaigns".
- Research on search/contextual advertising, computational advertising, ad auctions.
- Teaching Assistant & Technical Supervisor for postgraduate and undergraduate student dissertations and courses on Data Science, Machine Learning, Algorithms, Data Structures.

External Reviewer

- World Wide Web Conference (WWW), 2013
- European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML-PKDD), 2012
- IEEE/ACM Int. Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), 2012, 2013, 2014
- ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD), 2011

Awards

Microsoft

• Ship it! Award (Microsoft Internal Hackathon at Oslo 2014 - Expertify team: "Find the expert")

Athens University of Economics and Business

• Ph.D. Research Fund Heracleitus II European Union (European Social Fund - ESF)

Google

• Semi-finalist in the 2011 Google Online Marketing Challenge

National and Kapodistrian University of Athens

 1st award in the "Business Plan Contest" - "Education and Entrepreneurship" European program (2007)

Patents

Identifying experts and areas of expertise in an organization. (M. Platakis, C. Makris, T. Tonnesen Lied, B. Herstad, S. Thomaidou, S. Zitnik). Issued Apr 24, 2015 Patent issuer and number us US20160314122A1.

AD-MAD software (S.Thomaidou, Ecole Polytechnique - Paris & CNRS). Registered in March 2012 at the French agency for software protection (APP).

Publications

- S. Thomaidou, M. Vazirgiannis, K.Liakopoulos. Toward an Integrated Framework for Automated Development and Optimization of Online Advertising Campaigns. *Intelligent Data Analysis Journal. Volume* 18(6). *November* 2014.
- S. Thomaidou, I. Lourentzou, P. Katsivelis-Perakis, M. Vazirgiannis. Automated Snippet Generation for Online Advertising. ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM'13), San Francisco, USA.
- S. Thomaidou, K. Leymonis, M. Vazirgiannis. GrammAds: Keyword and Ad Creative Generator for Online Advertising Campaigns. *Digital Enterprise Design & Management Conference (DED&M'13)*, France, Paris.
- S. Thomaidou, K. Leymonis, K. Liakopoulos, M. Vazirgiannis. AD-MAD: Integrated System for Automated Development and Optimization of Online Advertising Campaigns. *IEEE International Conference on Data Mining Workshop (ICDMW'12)*, Brussels, Belgium. Demonstration using Adomaton and GrammAds
- K.Liakopoulos, S. Thomaidou, M. Vazirgiannis. The Adomaton Prototype: Automated Online Advertising Campaign Monitoring and Optimization. *Ad Auctions Workshop, ACM Conference on Electronic Commerce (AAW'12-EC'12)*, Valencia, Spain.
- S. Thomaidou, M. Vazirgiannis. Multiword Keyword Recommendation System for Online Advertising. *IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social Network Analysis and Mining (ASONAM'11)*, Kaohsiung, Taiwan.

INVITED TALKS

- S.Thomaidou. Her plus Data Meetup. Dublin, November 2017.
- S.Thomaidou. Data Science Challenges for Online Advertising. IWD Data mini-Conference. Dublin, March 2016.
- S.Thomaidou. Impact of technical sales on IBM's odds to win sales. IBM InterConnect 2015 Dublin.
- S. Thomaidou, K. Liakopoulos, M. Vazirgiannis. Automatic Advertising Campaign Development. Greek Free / Open Source Software Society (GFOSS) Technical Lab, April 2011. GRNET (Greek Research & Technology Network)

EDUCATION

Athens University of Economics and Business, Athens, Greece

Ph.D., Machine Learning and Data Mining, 2011 - 2014

- Thesis Topic: Automated Creation and Optimization of Online Advertising Campaigns
- Area: Search/contextual advertising, Computational advertising

M.Sc., Information Systems, 2009-2011

• Orientation: Business Information Systems

National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens, Greece

B.Sc., Computer Science, 2004-2009

 IBM

CERTIFICATION

TECHNICAL

Skills

• R, Python, SQL, SAS

Languages

Greek: Native, English, French

IBM Big Data Spark Foundations